<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Here after foloweth ye batayll of Egyngecourte [and] the great sege of Rone by kynge Henry of Monmouthe the fyfthe of the name that wan Gascoyne and Gyenne and Normandye</title>
            <title>Battle of Agincourt.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1536</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 18 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09522</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 198</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S90056</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853161</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853161</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18530</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09522)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18530)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 906:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Here after foloweth ye batayll of Egyngecourte [and] the great sege of Rone by kynge Henry of Monmouthe the fyfthe of the name that wan Gascoyne and Gyenne and Normandye</title>
                  <title>Battle of Agincourt.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Foster lane in saynt Leonardes parysshe by me Ioh[a]n Skot,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Inpryntyd at Londo[n] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1536?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from colophon; publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁶.</note>
                  <note>In this edition A2r line 2 ends: shalbe wonne.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry --  V, --  King of England, 1387-1422 --  Poetry.</term>
               <term>Agincourt (France), Battle of, 1415 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:18530:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 50 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:18530:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 50 -->
            <head>¶ Here after foloweth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> batayll of Egyngecourte &amp; the great ſege of Rone by kynge Henry of Mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouthe the fyfthe of the name that wan Gaſcoyne and Gyenne and Normandye.</head>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Od that all this worlde dyde make</l>
            <l>And dyed for vs vpon a tree</l>
            <l>Saue england for mary thy mothers</l>
            <l>As y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art ſtedfaſt god in trynyte</l>
            <l>And ſaue ky<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ry ſoule I beſeche y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſake</l>
            <l>That was full gracyouſe and good with all</l>
            <l>A courtyouſe knyght and kynge ryall</l>
            <l>Of Henry the fyfthe noble man of warre</l>
            <l>Thy dedes may neuer forgoten be</l>
            <l>Of knyghthod thou were the very lodeſtarre</l>
            <l>In thy tyme Englande floured in proſperyte</l>
            <l>Thou mortall myrrour of all cheualry</l>
            <l>Though thou be not ſet amonge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worthyes nyne.</l>
            <l>yet waſt thou a conqueroure in thy tyme</l>
            <l>Our kynge ſende in to Fraunce full rathe</l>
            <l>His harraude that was good and ſure</l>
            <l>He deſyred his herytage for to haue</l>
            <l>That is Gaſcoyne and Gyen and Normandye</l>
            <l>He bad the Dolphyne delyuer / it ſhulde be his</l>
            <l>All that belongyd to the fyrſt Edwarde</l>
            <l>And yf he ſayd me nay I wys</l>
            <l>I wyll get it with dent of ſwerde</l>
            <l>But than anſwered the Dolphyne bolde</l>
            <l>By our inbaſſatours ſendynge agayne</l>
            <l>Me thynke that your kynge is not ſo olde</l>
            <l>Warres great for to mayntayne</l>
            <l>Grete well he ſayd your comely kynge</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18530:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 51 -->
That is bothe gentyll and ſmall</l>
            <l>A tun full of tenys balles I wyll hym ſend</l>
            <l>For to play hym therwithall</l>
            <l>Than bethought our lordes all</l>
            <l>In Fraunce they wolde no lenger abyde</l>
            <l>They toke theyr leue bothe greate &amp; ſmall</l>
            <l>Tnd home to Englande gan they ryde</l>
            <l>To our kynge they tolde theyr tale to the ende</l>
            <l>What that the Dolphyne dyde to them ſaye</l>
            <l>I wyll hym thanke than ſayd the kynge</l>
            <l>By the grace of god yf I may</l>
            <l>Yet by his owne mynde this Dolphyne bolde</l>
            <l>To our kynge he ſent agaynne haſtely</l>
            <l>And prayed hym trewes for to holde</l>
            <l>For Ieſus loue that dyed on a tree</l>
            <l>Nay than ſayd our comely kynge</l>
            <l>For in to Fraunce wyll I wynde</l>
            <l>The Dolphyne angre I truſt I ſhall</l>
            <l>And ſuche a tenys ball I ſhall hym ſende</l>
            <l>That ſhall bere downe the hye rofe of his hall</l>
            <l>The kynge at weſtmynſter lay that tyme</l>
            <l>And all his lordes euerychone</l>
            <l>As they dyde ſet them downe to dyne</l>
            <l>Lordynges he ſayd by ſaynt Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
            </l>
            <l>To Fraunce I thynke to take my waye</l>
            <l>Of good councell I you praye</l>
            <l>What is your wyll that I ſhall done</l>
            <l>Shewe me ſhortly without delay</l>
            <l>The duke of Clarence anſwered ſone</l>
            <l>And ſayd my lege I councell you ſoo</l>
            <l>And other lordes ſayd we thynke it for the beſt</l>
            <l>With you to be redy for to goo</l>
            <l>Whyle that our lyues may endure &amp; leſt</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18530:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 51 -->
Gramercy ſyrs the kynge gan ſay</l>
            <l>Our ryght I truſt than ſhalbe wonne</l>
            <l>And I wyll quyte you yf I may</l>
            <l>Therfore I warne you bothe olde &amp; yonge</l>
            <l>To make you redy without delay</l>
            <l>To Southampton to take your waye</l>
            <l>At ſaynt Peters tyde at Lammas</l>
            <l>For by the grace of god and yf I maye</l>
            <l>Ouer the ſalte ſee I thynke to paſſe</l>
            <l>Great ordynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of gunnes the kynge let make</l>
            <l>And ſhypte them at London all at ones</l>
            <l>Bowes and arowes in cheſtes were take</l>
            <l>Speres and bylles / with yeen gunſtones</l>
            <l>And armynge dagars made for the nones</l>
            <l>With ſwerdes &amp; bucklers that were full ſure</l>
            <l>And harneys bryght that ſtrokes wolde endure</l>
            <l>The kynge to Southampton than dyde ryde</l>
            <l>With his lordes for no lenger wolde he dwell</l>
            <l>Fyftene. C. fayre ſhyppes there dyde hym abyde</l>
            <l>With goodly ſayles and to peaſtell</l>
            <l>Lordes of Fraunce our kynge they ſolde</l>
            <l>For a myllyant of golde as I harde ſay</l>
            <l>By Englande lytell pryſe they tolde</l>
            <l>Therfore theyr ſonge was welawaye</l>
            <l>Bytwene hampton and the yle of wyght</l>
            <l>Theſe goodly ſhyppes lay there at rode</l>
            <l>With maſt yardes a croſſe full ſemely of ſyght</l>
            <l>Ouer all the hauen ſprede a brode</l>
            <l>On euery paues acroſſe rede</l>
            <l>The waſtes decked with ſerpentynes ſtronge</l>
            <l>Saynt Georges ſtremers ſpred ouer hede</l>
            <l>With the armes of Englande hangynge all alonge</l>
            <l>Our kynge full haſtely to his ſhyppe yede</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18530:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 52 -->
And all other lordes of euery degree</l>
            <l>Euery ſhyp wayed his anker in dede</l>
            <l>With the tyde to haſt them to the ſee</l>
            <l>They hoyſed theyr ſayles ſayled a lofte</l>
            <l>A goodly fyght it was to ſee</l>
            <l>The wynde was good and blew but ſofte</l>
            <l>And fourth they wente in the name of the trynyte</l>
            <l>Theyr courſe they toke towarde Normandy</l>
            <l>And paſſed ouer in a daye and a nyght</l>
            <l>So in the ſeconde mornonge yerly</l>
            <l>Of that contrye they had a ſyght</l>
            <l>And euer they drew nere the coſte</l>
            <l>Of the day glad were they all</l>
            <l>And whan they were at the ſhore almoſt</l>
            <l>Euery ſhyp his anker let fall</l>
            <l>With theyr takyls they lau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ched many a longe bote</l>
            <l>And ouer hache threw them in to the ſtreame</l>
            <l>A thouſande ſhortly they ſawe a flote</l>
            <l>With men of armes that lyth dyde leme</l>
            <l>Our kynge landed at Cottaunſes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out delay</l>
            <l>On our lady euenth aſſumpcyon</l>
            <l>And to Hartflete they toke the way</l>
            <l>And muſtered fayre before the towne</l>
            <l>Our kynge his banner there dyde ſplay</l>
            <l>With ſtanderdes bryght and many penowne</l>
            <l>And there he pyght his tente adowne</l>
            <l>Full well broydered with armory gaye</l>
            <l>Fyrſt our comely kynges tente with the crowne</l>
            <l>And all other lordes in good aray</l>
            <l>My brother Clarence the kynge dyde ſay</l>
            <l>The toures of the towne wyll I kepe</l>
            <l>With her doughters and her maydens gay</l>
            <l>To wake the frenchemen of theyr ſlepe</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18530:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 52 -->
London he ſayd ſhall with hym mete</l>
            <l>And my gunnes that lyeth fayre vpon the grene</l>
            <l>For they ſhall playe with Harfflete</l>
            <l>A game at tennys as I wene</l>
            <l>God we to game for goddes grace</l>
            <l>My chyldren be redy euerychone</l>
            <l>For euery great gunne that there was</l>
            <l>In his mouthe he had a ſtone</l>
            <l>The Capytayne of Herfflet ſoone anone</l>
            <l>Vnto our kynge he ſent haſtely</l>
            <l>To knowe what his wyll was to done</l>
            <l>For to cume thyther with ſuche a meny</l>
            <l>Delyuer me the towne the kynge ſayd</l>
            <l>Nay ſayd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Capytayne by god &amp; by ſaynt Denys</l>
            <l>Than ſhall I wynne it ſayd our kynge</l>
            <l>By the grace of god and of his goodnes</l>
            <l>Some hard tennys balles I haue hyther brought</l>
            <l>Of marble and yren made full rounde</l>
            <l>I ſwere by Ieſu that me dere bought</l>
            <l>They ſhall bete the walles to the grounde</l>
            <l>Than ſayd the greate gunne</l>
            <l>Holde felowes we go to game</l>
            <l>Thanked be Mary and Ieſu her ſone</l>
            <l>They dyde the frenchemen moche ſhame</l>
            <l>Fyftene afore ſayd London tho</l>
            <l>Her balles full fayre ſhe gan out throwe</l>
            <l>Thyrty ſayd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeconde gun I wyll wyn &amp; I may</l>
            <l>There as the wall was mooſt ſure</l>
            <l>They bare it downe without nay</l>
            <l>The kynges doughter ſayd herken this playe</l>
            <l>Harken maydens nowe this tyde</l>
            <l>Fyue and forty we haue / it is no nay</l>
            <l>They bete downe the walles on euery ſyde</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18530:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 53 -->
The Normandes ſayd let vs not abyde</l>
            <l>But gowe in haſte by one aſſent</l>
            <l>Where ſo euer the gunſtones do glyde</l>
            <l>Our houſes in Herfftete is all to rent</l>
            <l>The englyſ ſhemenourbul warkes haue brent</l>
            <l>And women cryed alas that euer they were borne</l>
            <l>The frenchemen ſayd now be we ſhent</l>
            <l>By vs now the towne is forlorne</l>
            <l>It is beſt now theyrfore</l>
            <l>That we beſeche this englyſ ſhe kynge of grace</l>
            <l>For to aſſayle vs no more</l>
            <l>Leſte he dyſtroye vs in this place</l>
            <l>Than wyll we byd the Dolphyne make hym redy</l>
            <l>Or elles this towne deryuered muſt be</l>
            <l>Meſſengers went fourth by and by</l>
            <l>And to out kynge come they</l>
            <l>The lorde Corgraunte certaynly</l>
            <l>For he was Capytayne of the place</l>
            <l>And Gelam Bowſec with hym dyde hye</l>
            <l>With other lordes more and laſſe</l>
            <l>And whan they to our kynge come were</l>
            <l>Full lowly ſet them on theyr kne<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>Hayle comely kynge gan they ſaye</l>
            <l>Cryſte ſaue the from aduerſyte</l>
            <l>Of truſe we wyll beſeche the</l>
            <l>Vntyll that it be ſunday noone</l>
            <l>And yf we may not recouered be</l>
            <l>We wyll delyuer the towne</l>
            <l>Than ſayd our kynge full ſoone</l>
            <l>I graunte you grace in this tyde</l>
            <l>One of you ſhall fourthe anone</l>
            <l>And the re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>naunt ſhall with me abyde</l>
            <l>Theyr Capytayne toke his nexte waye</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18530:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 53 -->
And to Rone faſte gan he ryde</l>
            <l>The Dolphyne he had thought there to founde</l>
            <l>But he was gone he durſte not abyde</l>
            <l>For helpe the Capytayne beſought that tede</l>
            <l>Herfflete is loſt for euer and aye</l>
            <l>The walles ben beten downe on euery ſyde</l>
            <l>That we no lenger kepe it may</l>
            <l>Of counſeyll all he dyde them pray</l>
            <l>What is your wyll that I may done</l>
            <l>We muſt ordeyne the kynge hatayll by ſonday</l>
            <l>Or elles delyuer hym the towne</l>
            <l>The lordes of Rone to gyther dyde rowne</l>
            <l>And bad the towne ſhulde openly yelde</l>
            <l>The kyng of englande fareth as a lyon</l>
            <l>We wyll not mete with hym in the felde</l>
            <l>The Capytayne wolde than no longer abyde</l>
            <l>And to warde Harfflete came he ryght</l>
            <l>For ſo faſte he dyde ryde</l>
            <l>That he was there the ſame nyght</l>
            <l>And whan he to oure kynge dyde come</l>
            <l>Lowly he ſet hym on his kne</l>
            <l>Hayle comely prynce than dyde he ſay</l>
            <l>The grace of god is with the</l>
            <l>Here haue I brought the keys all</l>
            <l>Of Harfflete that is ſo to yall a cytye</l>
            <l>All is yours bothe chambre and hall</l>
            <l>And at your veyll for to be</l>
            <l>Thanked he Ieſu ſayd our kynge</l>
            <l>And Mary his mother truely</l>
            <l>Myne vncle Dorſet without lettynge</l>
            <l>Capytayne of Herfflete ſhall he be</l>
            <l>And all that is within the cytye</l>
            <l>A whyle yet they ſhall abyde</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18530:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 54 -->
To amende the walles in euery degre</l>
            <l>That is beten downe on euery ſyde</l>
            <l>And after that they ſhall out ryde</l>
            <l>To other townes ouer all</l>
            <l>Wyfe nor chylde ſhall not there abyde</l>
            <l>But haue them forthe bothe great &amp; ſmall</l>
            <l>One and twenty. M. men myght ſe</l>
            <l>whan they went out full fore dyde wepe</l>
            <l>The great gunnes &amp; ordynaunce truely</l>
            <l>Was brought in to Herfflete</l>
            <l>Great ſykenes amonge our hoſte was in good fay</l>
            <l>Whiche kylled many of our englyſſhemen</l>
            <l>There dyed by yonde .vii. ſcore vpon a day</l>
            <l>Alyue there was lefte but thouſandes .x.</l>
            <l>Our kynge hym ſelfe in to the caſtell yede</l>
            <l>And reſted hym there as longe as his wyll was</l>
            <l>At the laſte he ſayd lordes ſo god me ſpede</l>
            <l>Towarde Calayes I thynke to paſſe</l>
            <l>After that Herfflete was gotten that royall cytye</l>
            <l>Through the grace of god omnypotente</l>
            <l>Our comely kynge made hym redy ſoone</l>
            <l>And towarde Calayes fourthe he wente</l>
            <l>My brother Gloceſtre veramente</l>
            <l>Here wyll we no lenger abyde</l>
            <l>And Coſyn of yorke this is oure entent</l>
            <l>With vs fourth ye ſhall this tyde</l>
            <l>My Coſyn Huntyngdon with vs ſhall ryde</l>
            <l>And the Erle of Oxenforde with you thre</l>
            <l>The duke of Southfolke by our ſyde</l>
            <l>He ſhall come fourthe with his meny</l>
            <l>And the Erle of Deuounſhyre ſykerly</l>
            <l>Syr thomas harpynge that neuer dyde fayle</l>
            <l>The lorde Broke that come hartely</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18530:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 54 -->
And ſyr Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of cornewall</l>
            <l>Syr Gylberde Vmfrey that wolde vs auayle</l>
            <l>And the lorde clyfforde ſo god me ſpede</l>
            <l>Syr wyllyam Bouſer that wyll not fayle</l>
            <l>For all thy wyll helpe yf it be nede</l>
            <l>Our kynge rode fourth bleſſyd mought he be</l>
            <l>He ſpared neyther dale ne downe</l>
            <l>By waters greate faſt rode he</l>
            <l>Tyll he cam to the water of ſene</l>
            <l>The frenchemen threwe the brydge adowne</l>
            <l>That ouer the water they myght not paſſe</l>
            <l>Our kynge made hym redy than</l>
            <l>And to the towre of Turreyn wente more &amp; laſſe</l>
            <l>The frenchemen our kynge abought becaſt</l>
            <l>With batayles ſtronge on euery ſyde</l>
            <l>The duke of Orlyaunce ſayd in haſte</l>
            <l>The kynge of Englande ſhall abyde</l>
            <l>Who gaue hym leue this waye to paſſe</l>
            <l>I truſt that I ſhall hym begyle</l>
            <l>Full longe or he come to Calays</l>
            <l>The duke of Burbone anſweryd fone</l>
            <l>And ſwere by god &amp; by ſaynt Denys</l>
            <l>We wyll play them euerychone</l>
            <l>Theſe lordes of Englande at the tenys</l>
            <l>Theyr Gentylmen I ſwere by laynt Ihon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
            </l>
            <l>And archers we wyll ſell them greate plentye</l>
            <l>And ſo wyll we ryd them ſone</l>
            <l>Six for a peny of our monye</l>
            <l>Than anſwered the duke of Bare</l>
            <l>Wordes that were of greate pryde</l>
            <l>By god he ſayd I wyll not ſpare</l>
            <l>Ouer all the englyſſhemen for to ryde</l>
            <l>If that they dare vs abyde</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18530:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 55 -->
We wyll ouerthrowe them in fere</l>
            <l>And take them pryſoners in this tyde</l>
            <l>Than come home agayne to our dynere</l>
            <l>Henry our kynge that was ſo good.</l>
            <l>He prepared there full ryally</l>
            <l>Stakes he let hewe in a wood</l>
            <l>And ſet them before his archers verely</l>
            <l>The frenchemen our ordynaunce ganeſpye</l>
            <l>They that we ordeyned for to ryde</l>
            <l>Lyghted adowne with ſorowe truely</l>
            <l>So on theyr fote faſt gan abyde</l>
            <l>Our kynge wente vp vpon an hyll hye</l>
            <l>And loked downe to the valyes lowe</l>
            <l>He ſawe where the frenchemen came haſtely</l>
            <l>As thycke as euer dyde hayle or ſnowe</l>
            <l>Than kneled our kynge downe in that ſtounde</l>
            <l>And all his men on euery ſyde</l>
            <l>Euery man made acroſſe &amp; kyſſed the grounde</l>
            <l>And on theyr fete faſt ganne abyde</l>
            <l>Our kynge ſayd ſyrs what tyme of the day</l>
            <l>My lege they ſayd it is nye pryme</l>
            <l>Than go we to our iourney</l>
            <l>By the grace of Ieſu it is good tyme</l>
            <l>For ſayntes that lye in theyr ſhryne</l>
            <l>To god for vs they be prayenge</l>
            <l>All the relygyouſe of Englande in this tyme</l>
            <l>Ora pro nobis for vs they ſynge</l>
            <l>Saynt George was ſene ouer our hoſte</l>
            <l>Of very trouthe this ſyght men dyde ſe</l>
            <l>Downe was he ſente by the holygoſte</l>
            <l>To gyue our kynge the vyctory</l>
            <l>Than blewe the trompetes merely</l>
            <l>Theſe two batayles to gyther yede</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18530:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 55 -->
Our archers ſtode vp full hartely</l>
            <l>And made the frenchemen faſt to blede</l>
            <l>Theyr arowes went faſt without ony let</l>
            <l>And many ſhot they through out</l>
            <l>Thorugh habergyne breſtplate &amp; baſſenet</l>
            <l>A .xi. M. were ſlayne in that route</l>
            <l>Our gracyouſe kynge as I well knowe</l>
            <l>That day he fough with his owne hande</l>
            <l>He ſpared neyther hye ne lowe</l>
            <l>There was neuer kynge in no lande</l>
            <l>That euer dyd better on a daye</l>
            <l>Wherfore Englande may ſynge a ſonge</l>
            <l>Laus deo may we ſay</l>
            <l>And other prayers euer amonge</l>
            <l>The duke of Orlyaunce without nay</l>
            <l>That day was taken pryſonere</l>
            <l>The duke of Burbone alſo in fere</l>
            <l>And alſo the duke of Bare truely</l>
            <l>Syr Bergygaunte he gan hym yelde</l>
            <l>And other lordes of Fraunce many</l>
            <l>Lo thus out comely kynge conquered the fyld</l>
            <l>Be the grace of god omnypotent</l>
            <l>He toke his preſoners bothe olde &amp; yonge</l>
            <l>And to warde Calayes fourth he went</l>
            <l>He ſhypped there with good entent</l>
            <l>To Cauntorbury full fayre he paſſed</l>
            <l>And offered to ſaynt Thomas thryne</l>
            <l>And through Keut he rode in haſte</l>
            <l>To Eltam he cam all in good tyme</l>
            <l>And ouer blackeheth as he was rydynge</l>
            <l>Of the Cytye of London he was ware</l>
            <l>Hayle ryall Cytye ſayd our kynge</l>
            <l>Cryſte kepe the euer from ſorowe &amp; care</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18530:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 56 -->
And than he gaue that noble Cyte his bleſſyng<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>He prayed Ieſu it myght well fare</l>
            <l>To weſtmynſter dyde he ryde</l>
            <l>And the frenche pryſoners with hym alſo</l>
            <l>He raunſommed them in that tyde</l>
            <l>And agayne to theyr contrye he let them goo</l>
            <l>Thus of this matter I make an ende</l>
            <l>To theffecte of the batayll haue I gone</l>
            <l>For in this boke I cannot comprehende</l>
            <l>The greateſt batayll of all called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſege of Rome</l>
            <l>For that ſege laſted .iii. yere and more</l>
            <l>And there a rat was at .xl. pens.</l>
            <l>For in the Cytye the people hongered fore</l>
            <l>Women and chyldren for faute of mete were lore</l>
            <l>And ſome for payne bare bones were gnawynge</l>
            <l>That at her breſtes had .ii. chyldren ſoukynge</l>
            <l>Of the ſege of Rone it to wryte were pytye</l>
            <l>It is a thynge ſo lamentable</l>
            <l>Yet euery hye feeſt / our kynge of his charytye</l>
            <l>Gaue them meate to theyr bodyes comfortable</l>
            <l>And at the laſte / the towne wanne wout fable</l>
            <l>Thus of all as now I make an ende</l>
            <l>To the blyſſe of heuen god our ſoules ſende.</l>
            <trailer>¶ Thus endeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> batayll of Egyngcourt</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Inpryntyd at Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Foſter lane in ſaynt Leonardes paryſ ſhe by me Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Skot.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:18530:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 56 -->
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
